This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
>> [music]
>> Welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
This is Sriram Padmanabhan, your host.
Today, we have Jure Leskovec. He's a
professor of computer science at
Stanford University and a chief
scientist at Kumo.ai. He pioneered graph
neural networks and co-authored PyTorch
Geometric, the most widely used GNN
framework. At Pinterest, he served as a
chief scientist for 6 years deploying
graph learning systems that contributed
to 30 to 50% improvement in core metrics
and helped the company go public.
His CS224W
course on machine learning with graphs
has over 1 million views on YouTube.
He's now building relational
foundational models at Kumo.ai. Welcome
to the show, Jure.
>> Great to be here.
>> We want to kind of establish some of the
current patterns that lead up to what
we're going to talk about today and I
want to talk about predictive modeling,
right? Just as an overview, what is it,
how it powers fraud detection, where are
organizations with it today?
>> Yeah, so basically, predictive modeling
has been around for a very long time and
making accurate predictions is basically
the best way to make decisions, right?
So, how do we make predictions is that
we look at a bunch of operational
historical data, behavioral data that
every organization is storing and then
trying to identify patterns in the past
that predict that future. And if you
say, what are the use cases for this,
they are very diverse, right? It can be
about fraud detection in transactions in
financial institutions, it can be about
recommendations, product recommendations
in all kinds of settings, it might be
about predicting the risk of churn of a
customer, predicting what is the next
best action to take, what is the
lifetime value of a customer, all the
way to the health care where you could
say what's the risk of readmission if I
discharge this patient. What is the risk
to life to this patient in the next 24
hours, right? These are all this kind of
decision-making risk assessment type
questions that we humans are kind of
inherently very biased and are very bad
at estimating those probabilities. So,
that's why over time we build models
that are calibrated that can estimate
this type of risk probabilities, this
kind of forecasts, you know, how likely
my machine is going to fail, time series
forecasting, predictive maintenance.
This kind of everywhere across industry.
>> Mhm. And today, where are enterprises in
terms of their maturity level in
adopting and deploying these?
>> Yeah, that's a great point. And what I
would claim is this predictive modeling
has been kind of left in the past, all
right? We have these amazing
advancements in AI. And when we talk
about advancements in AI, we talk about
advancements in, let's say, natural
language understanding, reasoning, and
things like that. And we have Claude and
ChatGPT and things like that, right? And
then we also have computer vision,
video, we understand these type of, I
would say, two data modalities, which is
natural language and images video. But
if you think about these predictive
models and what kind of data they learn
over, it's all about operational data
that is usually stored in tables. It's
stored in databases. It's stored in data
warehouses. We have a product catalog,
which is a big table, every row is a
product, and then the columns describe
what are the properties of the product.
We have my customer catalog where for
every customer I have their information,
who they are, where they are, and things
like that. And then I also have, let's
say, another table that's like a
transactions table that says, "This
particular customer purchased this
particular product for this price at
this time," right? So, I have a third
table that kind of points to the
customer ID and points to the product
ID. Right? That's how this data is
organized, and I would argue that
today's AI models cannot really reason
or well over this type of data. So, what
are we left with? Right? Like what I
mean by this is you cannot put a table
of transactions into ChatGPT and ask it,
"Hey, how likely is this to be a fraud?"
Or, I don't know, throw in some
information about a customer and say,
"What is the customer going to buy
next?" You will get something that is
kind of common sense, okay? But, it's
very low performance. So, what people
are left with today is machine learning,
right? Which is this old technology of
manually building these models from
data, training them, and then deploying
them. Building these models, you need to
hire a bunch of data scientists. They
need to clean the data. We can go
through the process, but the point is
it's very expensive. about two full-time
employees per model that you are
building, and it takes about, I don't
know, half a year to build a model and
put it in production. So, we can go
through how complicated this is and why.
>> Yeah, I mean, yeah, I'm glad you
mentioned that, because what you said
about putting all this data in relation
databases, it's a pretty rigorous or
time-consuming task of normalization
that somebody has to go through. And it
sounds like even when they do that, you
only know about the model what you know,
and you don't know what you don't know.
Right? So, what are some things that get
lost, and you wouldn't even know about
it when you do this kind of
normalization and flattening? What gets
lost?
>> That's a great point, right? So, usually
we put this data, let's say this simple
example of customers, products, and and
their purchases, orders, transactions,
right? Usually we would put this into a
database or into a data warehouse, uh
and then we run SQL queries over that.
And SQL queries, they're really good at
telling me what happened last week, what
happened last month. Um
I can ask all kinds of historical
questions, but it's less about that and
the prediction is not about
understanding the history, it's about
understanding the future. So, what do I
have to do, let's say, as a data
scientist? Is I cannot just train a
model over these three tables and say,
"Just learn over these tables and tell
me whether a customer will churn. What's
the risk of that?" Right? What I have to
do is I have to manually, for example,
take the customer, take their
transaction history, and then somehow I
need to aggregate that transaction
history into what is called a feature. I
need to basically do the table
flattening. I need to do feature
engineering. I need to summarize your
past purchases into some count, into
some numbers, so I can say, "How much
did you purchase last week? How much did
you purchase last month?" Then I can
say, "How much did you purchase on
Mondays? How about Tuesdays? How about
Wednesdays? How about mornings? How
about afternoons?" And then it's maybe
what's the sum of purchase prices?
What's your median purchase price?
What's the most expensive product you
bought? What's the cheapest one? And all
these variables we can use 2 hours here.
>> Yeah.
>> For me to just go through this, they
could be predictive of your likelihood
of churn, right? And now I only
connected the user, the customer, with
their transaction history. How about the
products? Right now, if I go to the
products, I'm like, "What types of
products? What categories? How well are
those products rated? Do they have a
high star rating? Do they have a low
star rating? Are those products
popular?" And so on, right? So, it's
like this infinite possibility of
signals that I, as human or as my coding
agent, could engineer into this big
training table, so I could then train
the model. And basically training the
model maybe is easy, but where it gets
complicated is when this model is
running, let's say, in production, when
it's making these predictions, all of
these signals need to be updated. Right?
If I make one more transaction, all my
counts of transactions, all my
aggregations of transactions, all they
need to be updated because everything
changed because I added a new
transaction.
Right? So, you start seeing how is this
getting complicated because then on the
fly, the signals need to be updated with
every single transaction, with every
single update to the database, all these
downstream calculations need to be spun
off because everything changes because
there's a new piece of information. And
there is other problems with this
flattening where, as you hinted,
essentially you are losing information,
right? There is more information in,
let's say, in the raw sequence than
there is in the count over the last 7
days.
Count over last 7 days is some arbitrary
construct that we humans are like,
"Okay, probably if if I count how much
you purchased last week, that will
likely tell me something useful about
you purchasing in the future as well."
But it's a guess. So, I have to first
engineer the feature, put it in the
model, retrain the model, and then see,
"Oh, did it help or not?" Yes, it helped
a bit. Okay, fine. All right? And then,
if you, for example, start thinking
broader, right? If you think about
let's say, fraud detection. Fraud
detection is an adversarial game.
So, whatever model you are using to
predict fraud, the other side figures
that out and tries to game you.
Because it games you, your model
accuracy starts decreasing. And then you
are like, "Okay, what signal am I
missing to detect these new types of
fraud?" And you put it in, they discover
it, and you are behind again. And you
are again scratching the head, "What
another signal do I need to do to do
this?" Right? So, it's super painful,
super manual, super expensive. And
studies show that most of these models
never see production because it's so old
school. It's like 30 years old
technology. We've been doing this the
same way for 30 years. Maybe we changed
the architecture that we train on this
data, but the architecture is not the
problem. The problem is this manual
process of flattening the tables,
engineering the features, training these
models,
putting these models in production by
needing to update all these features in
real time as events are happening. And
then you have problems with what
information leakage or this time
correctness because you know, maybe I
have a mistake and I also count the
transaction you'll make tomorrow. And
then of course, from data about
tomorrow, I can predict tomorrow very
accurately, but you don't catch that and
then your models don't perform the way I
you expected and so on. So it's a I
would say data science and this model
building with machine learning is very,
very hard, very, very hard to get very
wrong on.
>> So in a way, you can take a relational
database, you can
manually create the views and
materialized views and triggers and all
that, right? To make it look like a
graph, but really the devil's in the
details because doing that is pretty
complicated and a lot of work, right? It
sounds like your thesis is if you can do
all that work to take something that's
normalized and turn that into a graph
after all this burning of energy, why
not start with a graph?
>> Exactly. So my thesis is the following,
right? The first thing is that
tabular data, this relational data, is
the key to enterprise decision making.
>> Mhm.
>> Right? We collect it, it's the most
valuable data because we want to make
accurate decisions at all levels, right?
And even in agentic world, agents need
to make decisions and those decisions
have to be driven in data and historical
patterns. They are not common sense type
things most often, right? So that's the
first thing is this is amazingly
valuable. Second thing that I want to
say is that today's AI does not
understand this type of data well. You
cannot textify a database, put it as a
prompt in chat GPT, and expect it to
work. People have tried that, they
burned themselves badly. All right, so
it's kind of a missing data modality in
today's AI. So, how do you then solve
the problem? That was the key, let's
say, question or insight that I asked
myself and my students here at Stanford
and said, we have to do something in
this area, it's left behind. So, we
developed this approach, we call it a
relational deep learning, that basically
says, we can take a database, a set of
tables, we can represent it as a graph
of linkages, and now we can develop
special architectures that
generalize this attention mechanism that
is prevalent in text transformers, where
we are attending over the tokens, the
words from the past, to now generalize
this to attend over the
tables in a database.
And if we can have now a neural network
that attends over the raw tables in a
database, and just it basically figures
out how to pull all these data together
into an accurate prediction, there are
two benefits. First benefit is that you
get an amazing productivity gain,
because you don't have to do this
flattening of data into a single table,
and you can build these models faster.
The second improvement is that your
models get kind of superhuman accuracy.
And the reason for that is that, as I
mentioned earlier, when you take a
sequence of transactions and aggregate
it into a transaction count over the
last 7 days, you have thrown away a lot
of information. So, attention mechanism
that attends actually over a sequence of
transactions
has much more fidelity, has much more
finesse to it, to actually learn how to
combine this information, how to attend
over these transactions. Is it 7 days?
Is it mornings? Is it evenings? Let the
attention mechanism figure that out to
combine that data in an optimal way that
is most predictive downstream. And, of
course, it's not only
because it's a graph, it's multiple
tables, it's not just oh, it's a
sequence modeling. No, it's more because
it's recursive, right? A sequence of
transactions connects to a sequence of
products. Those products connect to
other transactions that connect to other
users. So, now you are attending through
this graph essentially to understand and
to reason over the data in a database.
That's the exciting thing is that you go
from a person to transaction to the
product to another transaction to
another person. All of a sudden, you can
be like, "Okay, what are the
characteristics of people that buy the
same products as I buy?" There's useful
information there.
>> Mhm.
>> Right? And so on and so forth. That's
the thesis.
>> That's interesting because if you again
going back to classical, I guess,
transformers, you're attending over a
sequence of tokens in text, right?
What does a token look like in this
model? I mean, what is conceptually
we've been thinking about tokens in text
as, you know, three, four letters,
three, four characters. There's some
kind of arbitrary boundary, right? What
becomes your unit of attending over in
this model? Like, what is a token here?
>> Great question. A token here, you have
two options. One option is to think of
every cell in a database as token.
So, every row column combination, right?
An age of a particular user, uh location
of a particular user, gender of a
particular user, and so on, right? Those
could be the tokens. Or you can think of
entire row as a token. So, a user is a
token, a transaction is a token, a
product is a token that then gets
attended over. And actually, in reality,
that's maybe the way to see it. In
reality, it's a bit more complicated,
but probably the best way to think is
that now we are attending over
individual cells
and as well as how they point to each
other. That's the key differentiator is
that we're not only attending over
individual cells, but also over the
relationships between the cells, right?
That one row points to another row. so I
know that this particular user points to
this particular transaction and that
transactions point to a particular
product that has a given set of
entities. So, the attention mechanism is
different. It's not sequence based, but
it's like graph based. So, you need to
understand these relationships and
pointers. Understanding this relational
structure is super crucial, especially
when the data is noisy or in cold start
type regimes where you don't have enough
information, then through this
relational context, the model is able to
hone in and make much more accurate
predictions than traditional approaches.
>> Because you know, I mean, to my ear it
keeps getting blown away. Going I'm
going back to our price transformer,
right? Simple tokens, simple embeddings.
So, what would then be your embedding
model or your tokenizer model because
you have a lot more volatility and
variation in what a token is, right? In
a simple text like the cats sat on the
mat, right? You have a much more narrow
or more limited token space, right? But
here, almost it sounds like almost every
combination, every entity, every entity
relationship, you potentially have an
unbounded token space then, don't you?
>> Great point. You have an unbounded token
space. You don't say, "Oh, you know, I
have this fixed vocabulary of tokens as
you do in LLMs." Here, you have in this
respect an infinite number of tokens,
right? Or token combinations because
cells can take arbitrary values. There
can be text in there. There can be
images in there. So, in this respect,
you don't have this kind of explicit
tokens, but what are you attending over
are the values of the cells. In this
respect, you're right, the token space
is infinite because I'm attending over
the values of individual cells.
>> Mhm. I mean, technically even in
English, you have a fairly large token
space. We just approximate it down, I'm
guessing.
>> For example, right? Or at the end we can
say, "Okay, we have characters and
there's letters of the alphabet." And
that's it, right?
>> Mhm.
>> Everything is made out of that.
>> So, does then the attention mechanism
itself have a different meaning because
again, going back to relational
transformers, you have your n squared
attention for every token versus every
token very very conceptually and dumbed
down, right? What then here would be the
complexity or space complexity of this
attention mechanism over this graph kind
of tokens?
>> Yeah, it's different, right? Because you
don't think of this as oh, I have now
this sequence of tokens and I do
everything to everything type attention.
What you are doing is now that your
attention mechanism is much more
structured. Maybe inside a given row of
the table, you are attending everything
to everything. So, you have let's say a
row based attention. Then you have also
a column based attention where a given
column is attending to other columns, to
other rows, other values of the same
column to get a sense of what is the
distribution of values, right? So,
that's also quadratic, but it's kind of
quadratic in some band of the number of
rows. The other one is kind of quadratic
in the maybe the number of columns per
table, not the total data. And then you
also have the attention across tables
that again is highly structured, is not
everything to everything, but it's just
across the links that actually exist
among the entities. So, you basically
have three different types of attention
that is I would say highly structured.
So, you can process large amounts of
tokens because it's not that any token
in a database can attend to any other
token as in text, but you are attending
inside a row, inside a column, and
across the tables.
>> Is this a design feature or design
trade-off?
>> Good question. I would say it's a design
feature because it allows you to scale,
allows you to be computationally
bounded, and it's a good way to actually
respect how the data is organized and
how the data is linked.
>> Interesting. So, as I put a mental model
this, you may have hundreds of tables
with thousands or millions of fact
actions and dependencies across these
tables. You wouldn't brute-force your
way by taking everything, but you would
build out these aggregations, these
relationships, you know, into a graph.
Again, through the model or through
automatically. And then see which
relationships or which connections have
some kind of waiting, some kind of
higher relevance, I guess, right? So,
these aggregations being building, these
relationships being formed, these
connections being actively computed.
What is doing that? What is doing it?
How does it happen? I'm assuming that's
not a manual process, right?
>> Great point. In our approach, this is
not a manual process. Basically, we
would start from a set of tables and a
set of, let's say, primary foreign key
type relationships or relationships
between tables where we know that one
column in one table points to another
column in the other table. And from
there on, the process of training is
essentially automatic. Because, as I
said, basically these three types of
attention mechanism that we have
developed, one inside a row of a single
table, the other one across the rows, so
basically inside a single column of a
table, and then the third type of
attention is over the primary foreign
key relations from pointing from one
table to another table. And we basically
now have We stack together multiple
layers of this type of attention, and
then train now this architecture, we
call it a relational transformer, with
some downstream loss.
>> Interesting. So, just to kind of
summarize that, if you were to take your
tables, your rows, and your foreign
keys, your table schemas become your
node types or node private, I guess type
parameters. Your rows become your actual
nodes, and your foreign keys like it
become edges, right, between these rows
and a table. So, in a way, do you
actually have parameterized nodes or are
all nodes just nodes?
>> Great point. I think you summarized it
very nicely. Nodes are parameterized,
right, because you can think of all the
column information, all the properties
of a product, all the properties of a
user to be attributes or data attached
to these nodes. So, what is beautiful in
this case is now that the attention
mechanism is both learning from the
properties as well as from the
relationships.
And that's where the power of these
methods comes in.
>> Nice. I want to slightly switch to
something those there before. I mean,
precursor, I guess, something history.
Graph neural networks,
right? I mean, they somehow tied to this
because this graphs, this neural
networks, what is the significance of
those in this journey, in this
transformation, in this evolution?
>> Yeah, that's a great point. I would say
graph neural networks were a very
important first step in this area where
we are talking about maybe smaller
models with predefined aggregations
rather than attending over the, let's
say, individual transactions. We would
be like just having some transformation
and then a pooling aggregator like a
summation or an average kind of more
old-school type neural network
architecture. And those models were
good, accurate, but of course, the new
generation of models that are
attention-based, kind of attention is
all you need, that scale better with
parameter size, becomes important. And
graph neural networks in particular have
this issue of what is called over
smoothing or over squashing where,
because if you think a bit about it from
this kind of attention point of view,
right? When I'm trying to make a
prediction about the node and if I go
too far away from in the graph, in the
neighborhood around that node, you can
think kind of as a ball around or a
circle around the node, then the problem
with graph neural networks was that they
were not rich enough in terms of their
expressivity, so they started just kind
of averaging things together. If you
average over a too big circle of things,
you kind of always get the same value.
That started to be a problem. It's
called technically over smoothing, but
with the attention-based architectures,
the degrees of freedom and the finesse
kind of of the attention mechanism is so
much larger that this over-smoothing
effect is not a factor anymore.
>> Do you have a real-world example of what
that looks like and it does
over-smoothing? I mean, I think you
deployed at Pinterest. What might that
look like?
>> Yeah, so for example, in graph neural
networks, right? We built a system and
deployed this very successfully at
Pinterest. And what usually meant in
graph neural networks is that if you
think about how many hops away in the
graph you go, you must not go too many
hops away. Because if you kind of go too
many hops away, then you reach the
entire graph and it's just too much
information that is
You can think of it this way, right?
Like imagine if I want to predict
something about you or about myself,
knowing information about my friends is
very useful. Knowing information about
my friends of friends is still useful.
But if you think about should I now go
10 friendships apart, then basically I
reach every person on the earth because
of the 6° of separation. And knowing
information about every person on the
earth to say about something like me can
kind of be over-confusing or
overpowering the model. That's kind of
maybe one intuition for this
over-smoothing problem phenomena of
graph neural networks.
>> And we couldn't just put a cap or put
some kind of arbitrary limit on how deep
you wanted to go or what was that?
>> That was the solution is don't go too
deep. Go two, three hops, get the
information that is relevant, and then
build a model on that. That was kind of
the attitude with graph neural networks.
Now, with attention-based architectures,
we don't have to do that.
>> Interesting, interesting. With
attention-based architectures, right?
How does that decide which neighbors to
pay, how deep to go, what kind of
subgraphs to kind of go over? What is
the deciding factor or I guess logic
there?
>> That is a great point. I would say you
have kind of the In some sense, you can
think of it as a context window size.
You can make that large, put the data
in, and then let the training process
figure out how to attend. There is still
a couple of kind of hyper parameters one
can tune, how wide to go, how deep to
go. But what we see is that the
attention mechanism is not prone to over
smoothing and can deal with large
context sizes quite effectively.
I would also say that this large context
size becomes very important because of
now the latest exciting thing in this
area is this notion of a foundation
model and this notion of in-context
learning where you need to be able to
work with large context sizes.
>> Mhm. Fair enough. I think you thought
about this in terms of foundation models
and attention, right?
From a training perspective, one thing
that both graph and neural networks and
relation kind of foundation models share
with your usual LLMs is data hungriness,
right? But it sounds like with graph
transformers you can actually not be as
hungry. Why is that? What causes it?
>> Yeah, I think you're asking a great
question and I think here is where this
tabular and data and also the nature of
prediction gets a bit different from the
large language models where bigger is
better, the more you can kind of
memorize, the more of the world you
know, the better things are. Here things
are a bit different, right? Because
depending on the amount of data, you may
choose different approaches, right? If
you have a larger amount of data, think
about fraud detection or something like
that that is also running or uh think of
a recommend system that is running at
speed of a million recommendations per
second, right? So you really need
accurate recommendations, you know
exactly the predictive question you'll
be asking, and you want it to be
cost-effective. In this type of cases,
you would usually go and fine-tune a
small model that is really good at that
single task. Because I won't go and ask
that fraud detection model to do
customer churn prediction. That's a
separate problem. So, we would say,
"Okay, I want I have a single task. It's
a super high-valuable task. I want to
have a small, dedicated, cheap-to-run
model that does this very well for you."
Right? And the important point is that
in these domains, 1 to 2% increase in
accuracy of decision-making model for
fraud or for recommendations, I've seen
clients where this means hundreds of
millions of dollars in additional
revenue. Just because you're doing it so
often and the effect just adds up.
Right? So, that's one side. The other
side is this notion of foundation
models, where what you can do now that
is actually quite exciting and in some
sense unbelievable is that you get this
chat GPT-type moment, but for predictive
problems, where you can specify the
predictive problem on the fly, the model
goes, fetches your relational data, and
without any model training, gives you an
accurate prediction. Okay? So, basically
now you have a pre-trained model that is
agnostic of the database and is agnostic
of the predictive task. So, you can ask
it, "Predict churn for me." And churn
means no purchase next 30 days. A second
later, you get the prediction, you get
the accuracy estimate, you get a natural
language-based explanation. Then
somebody says, "No, no, for me churn
means less than $10 of monthly spend." A
second later, you get now prediction for
the probability of less than $10 monthly
spend. That's a different capability,
where basically you can have a large
pre-trained model, you don't know the
question ahead of time, and you can just
ask it. You don't have to build now a
prediction-specific model, the
pre-trained model can give you the
answer immediately.
>> This is actually pretty wild. Now, if
you look at your, again, chat GPT, the
the usual go-to example, I guess, right?
I think now you train that model or a
cluster of, I think, 4 to 5 billion
dollars worth of GPUs or a few months of
runs and using exabytes of data, right?
Train the model. What is the training
data size for a foundational graph model
here? Is actually in the same scale,
different scale? What are we looking at?
>> That's a great point. I would say right
now, let's say the tabular relational
side of the world is younger than LLM
world. People are working on scaling
things up, but so far we've seen that
you don't need the scale as you have in
large language models. You can train
with a smaller amounts of data with much
less cost and these models can be
smaller, you know, like sub-billion
parameter models or something like that.
So, they can be small. And the reason
for that is because the information is
in the data. So, you don't have to
memorize, you don't have to learn the
entire internet worth of knowledge. You
just need to learn how to spot patterns,
how to attend over them to give the
prediction. And because of that, the
models are smaller, right? For example,
the single table models, I think they're
around 25 million parameters.
>> Wow.
>> Right, which is tiny. It It runs on my
iPhone kind of, right? So, those are
small. Relational are bigger, the ones
that can do multiple tables at once, but
still, this is not 100 million or a
trillion parameters.
>> What's the biggest, most complex model
that you might find out there?
>> I would say the field is moving very
fast. We are innovating and researching
very fast. And there is a lot of, I
would say also, different approaches. I
don't think here the final word or the
final solution has kind of been
converged. So, I would say right now, I
told you about kind of the sizes of
these single table models. Relational
models are larger, but an order of
magnitude. It becomes interesting the
next generation architectures that we
are exploring that actually may go even
bigger. But the point is, you need to
get benefit from getting bigger. You
need to start seeing scaling laws and
then it makes sense to scale up.
>> My point was kind of in reverse. It
almost sounds like somebody with the
know-how, but today the know-how is a
limitation, not the capex. So, if I had
the know-how, I could technically train
a model on my MacBook.
Again, I am mathematically nowhere close
to it. I am not one of those people, but
it is not beyond the realms of
practicality to to so, right? And still
have a state-of-the-art foundation model
that is mine.
>> Maybe that's a bit too optimistic.
>> Okay. Okay.
>> You need to spend some good amount on
proper latest generation Nvidia
hardware.
>> Right. But not $5 million worth of GPUs.
>> But not $5 million worth of GPUs. Let's
say millions of dollars. Let's say you
need to be in millions of dollars of
investment.
>> Right. So, technically a bank, for
example, again, they wouldn't do it,
they shouldn't do it, but they may be a
reason for them to say, "Look, for a
billion for for a couple of million
dollars, I can actually do a fully
optimized in personalized in-house
foundation model, from which we can
further train our own use cases for
competitive advantage."
>> Exactly. And at my company Kumon.ai, we
see a lot of traction for this.
>> Nice. Nice.
>> Exactly what you said.
>> The IEEE Computer Society is now
accepting candidates for the new
software professional certification.
Whether you're leveling up or ready to
lead teams, this certification validates
your expertise. Backed by the industry's
most trusted professional organization
in computing.
Visit computer.org/certification
to sign up today.
>> I do want to touch back on one thing
that I forgot to mention earlier. Again,
with with graphs, edges matter.
What about the history? What about time
series data? Like I mean, isn't there a
meant to be uh marriage of the two for
actually breaking the future?
>> Time series data is interesting, right?
Like you can say okay, if you think that
time series are
>> let's say independent of each other,
then you could say time series is a
sequence, right? But reality gets more
complicated very quickly because time
series are correlated with each other.
Time series are connected with each
other, right? Two products in the same
product category might be competing with
each other. So, what I'm trying to tell
you now is basically that time series
prediction problem is also a graph
problem because if I only attend over a
sequence of sales of a given product, I
cannot, for example, learn that sales of
this product is correlated with the
sales of this other product and with
this way have more information to do
more accurate prediction, right? So,
even time series forecasting in reality,
when you actually look how the data is
organized and all that, it's not that
here is an individual time series, tell
me what happens next. No, here is a set
of time series about this set of, let's
say, products, assets. Here is how these
assets are connected. Here is all their
properties. And again, it becomes a
graph problem. So, this type of
approaches work really well for time
series prediction as well. And the
reason why we think of time series as an
individual type of thing is because
that's what today's technology allows us
to do. We have a hammer and we are
looking for the nail. But I'm saying
with a more general hammer, nails also
change.
>> Well, I think I was not clear there. I
just agree with you on that. I'm I'm
just saying
it wasn't clear to me on how the graph
or foundation models today would encode
time series information as well because
even time series data changes
relationships over time. At T0, product
one will affect T0 product two, and then
that will affect T1 product one, and so
on, right? So, there is graph
relationships even within time series
data. And is that somehow being captured
today or exploited today
in this new paradigm?
>> That is a great point. I would say today
there are time series foundation models
which are basically sequence
transformers that attend and predict on
the individual time series. And I think
we both agree that that is limiting
because of relationships between time
series. And if you can learn over those
relationships, you just automatically
get more signal and your accuracy
increases. So, definitely these
graph-based approaches we've seen work
really well with time series supply
chain type information and so on.
>> I want to kind of contrast some of the
complexities, right? If you take graph
learning or graph foundation models,
right? And then compare that with let's
say your traditional resistance.
From a training time perspective,
resource perspective, how would you
contrast those two? LLMs on the other
hand are pretty heavy on this side, but
in the same space, how would you
compare? What are the contrasts?
>> Yeah, it's interesting. I think today
for majority of predictive modeling,
it's actually not the training time
that's the bottleneck. It's all these
data munging, ETL,
>> data
>> pipelines that are actually running on
CPUs and are very slow and sluggish. And
the models that we train on top, those
are quite quick to train. So, the
difference here is that we say, "Skip
the ETL, take a beefy model, GPU-based,
and just let it train directly on the
raw data." And I want to make a point,
right? It's like earlier I made claims,
you can now build models faster, you can
get 10-20% better accuracy, and people
are like, "Why? How?" And my point is,
we shouldn't be surprised about this.
The same steps carried out twice
already. First, they carried out in
computer vision, and then they carried
out in, let's say, natural language
understanding. And if you look at
computer vision, I could say, if I joke
a bit, right? I'm building a detector
whether there is a cow on the image or
not. Of course, you could say, "If me,
computer vision expert, I can engineer a
perfect feature for whether there's a
cow on the image or not, then my
classifier will be amazing."
We are both smiling now because we both
know that it's kind of impossible to
human-engineer a perfect feature for is
there a cow in the image or not, right?
So, all these feature-based approaches
that we would do, I don't know, sift
features, Gabor filters, and so on,
where you would then train a neural
network or a support vector machine or
whatever it was to detect whether there
is a cow on the image or not, you don't
do this today. You just have a a vision
transformer or a, you know, in the old
days you had a convolutional neural
network that just attends over all the
pixels
and figures out how to combine all this
scattered spread information across the
pixels into is it a cow or not. What I'm
doing here or proposing is the same.
Don't try to engineer the perfect
feature. Let the attention mechanism
attend over your database the same way
as it attends over the pixels
and let it extract that information out.
So, in this respect, I'm kind of saying
very obvious things that we've seen work
in the past and maybe the only thing I'm
saying is
as soon as you think of a database as a
graph,
you can do it.
Before, we didn't know how to represent
the database to be able to kind of
attend over it. We didn't know what the
pixels are. And now I'm saying, "Think
of it as a graph. Nodes are your pixels
and there are relationships between
them. Just attend over that." It's more
complex than computer vision because
there is no this spatial locality and
things like that, but it's very doable
and very fruitful.
>> I can go back to I think when you said
treat the database as a graph, that I
guess triggered something for me in a
good way. When you have a prediction
query or prediction request or
prediction session coming in, right?
What does the data access pattern look
like in your database? From the audition
mechanism, from the model perspective,
from the flow perspective.
>> That's a great point. So, what the data
access mechanism essentially is, as
events are coming in, you need to keep
the graph up to date. And then all you
need to do is basically fetch like a
local neighborhood around the node of
interest, right? So, you need to
basically fetch a small subset of your
database, data from a couple of tables,
send that through the neural network,
through this transformer-based
architecture, to get a prediction.
And what is a huge difference here is
that once the model is trained,
putting it in production is trivial.
You just refresh the raw data. There's
no feature pipelines, no feature stores,
no that additional computation that
needs to be done every time a
transaction appears. You just take the
latest data, pump it through the neural
network, and you get the latest
prediction.
>> So, how do databases need to adapt and
evolve to allow these patterns to be
visible to the model or I guess the
agent, right? We can go full graph DBs,
right? Or we can have more specialized
indexes on the current graphs, but
something's going to break.
>> That is a great point. So, I would
actually say to me there are
two solutions here. If you don't need
too much QPS, then you can basically
just keep the data in Postgres or MySQL
or in Snowflake or whatever you have it,
and we can basically do this push down
to extract the data on the fly through
essentially running the SQL statements.
If you need performance, scale, and
things like that, and short latency, or
if the mass of predictions you need to
make is super large,
basically the graph databases, the
current graph databases, are not the
right approach because they've been
built for a different type of workload.
They've been built for this kind of
sparkle-like queries and for building
the graphs and querying them. They
haven't been built for the AI workloads.
So, what we see is that today's graph
databases are about an order two orders
of magnitude too slow to actually
support this type of predictive AI use
cases.
>> On the read or write path or both paths?
>> Mostly on the read.
>> Okay.
>> On just extracting these subgraphs out.
So, what we've built at Kumo is a
specialized
system built ground up.
You can think of it as a graph database
that is purpose-built for these AI
workloads for high-volume, large-scale
predictions that can be run and has been
adopted at kind of the largest
internet-scale enterprises here in
Silicon Valley and beyond.
>> Nice, nice. I know you have talked about
PyTorch Geometric. I know it's sort of a
tangent, but how did it come about? What
was the origin story? Where is it today?
>> That's a great point. So, PyTorch
Geometric basically came out of this
idea. This was back in 2017, 2019,
something like that, right? Like when
deep learning was raising up, it was
computer vision, transformers were kind
of there, but not yet. And then there
was a lot of problems that don't fit
into this fixed grid of pixels. They
don't fit into a sequence, but they fit
into the graph. And this is a lot of
problems in let's say spatial data,
computer graphics, chemistry, social
networks, graphs, and so on. And there
was really a need to build an
open-source package where researchers
could build latest architectures,
benchmark them with each other, and for
the community to make progress. So, we
built PyG or PyTorch Geometric as the
library. It has, I think, like now 20
plus thousand GitHub stars and things
like that. That really catalyzed the
research in this area of graph neural
networks and graph transformers. We
built also benchmarks. One of them was
called OGB, Open Graph Benchmark as we
called it, large-scale graphs. And now
for relational data, we are building
what we call a RelBench, which is a set
of databases and a set of predictive
tasks over them. And all are publicly
accessible so that we can benchmark
progress and see what methods work and
which don't. And I would say for PyG was
also great because we have great
collaborations with Nvidia as well as
Intel in the past, where we said, "Okay,
this has to run efficiently, scalably on
the latest hardware." And those
partnerships and that support with
Nvidia, with the PyTorch team and so on
means that the open-source library is
actually useful and performant.
>> You mentioned Nvidia and hardware
companies. Are you finding that there
are other kind of demands or
expectations that would serve relational
foundational models better
from a hardware perspective than let's
say
what they currently serving today, which
is the LLM use case, right? Or are you
making do with what's coming out, the
usual H100s and
>> Yeah, and B200s and so on, yeah. That's
a great point. Working with graphs, I'd
say it's an order of magnitude harder
than working with these linear data
types, right? Text is nice, it's a
sequence, you can chop it, you can just
linearly scan through a GPU. Image is
essentially it's a fixed-size matrix.
Each images are independent from each
other, so again, you can kind of push
them through or video in the same way.
But graphs are hard, right? Graphs, they
have no up and down, they don't have any
left and right, there's no way to chop
them into pieces. Everything is kind of
connected and interdependent, you don't
know what is going to connect with what.
So dealing with graphs is very, very
hard. And this means that you have to be
very careful how you design the systems
to be scalable and to actually take
advantage of today's hardware. And I
would say through Stanford we're
actually working with Nvidia quite a lot
in terms of them understanding what are
the needs
for the future chips as we move beyond
sequential LLMs. And memory access
patterns become very different because
you are essentially almost like randomly
accessing different nodes in memory,
pulling those together, and you want to
keep your GPUs utilized.
>> Mhm. Can you give us a peek at what's
coming?
>> I can say that we've been discussing and
brainstorming what would allow us to
process these types of interconnected
data in a proper way, and it's a lot
about defining the benchmarks and
running simulations, running
measurements to understand how can these
data access patterns be better supported
by the underlying, I would say, software
as well as the hardware.
>> Mhm. Interesting. And I guess in a way,
given that we're talking about not
exabytes of data, not the amount of data
volume at the same scale as LLMs,
there's opportunity for even more
specific hardware to come out of this.
Is that fair?
>> It's interesting, right? I think these
enterprise data sets get big very, very
quickly.
>> Mhm.
>> Right? Maybe they are not internet
scale, but they get big very, very
quickly if you start thinking about, I
don't know, all the transactions on the
Bitcoin blockchain, right? Now, all the
clicks and all the comments made by all
the users of Reddit. These amounts of
data get very big. Or if you start
thinking about banks, financial
institutions, transactions, and
everything that's going on there, that's
huge velocity and volumes of data.
Easily petabytes and up.
>> Nice.
You know, in the aspect of foundation
models, it's when you think LLMs, we
think we are all now implicitly aware of
our how experience hallucinations,
right? What does hallucination mean in
the context of RFMs?
Is it there? It's not there. It's look
differently. What does it mean?
>> That's a great point. I think what is
different in relation of foundation
models because they are making a
prediction, we make sure that that
prediction is calibrated so that we
properly give the estimate of
uncertainty and also get back a sense of
accuracy. So, in this respect, it is not
hallucinated, but basically you get an
accurate estimate of how sure we how
accurate is this prediction. And then
with that, you can then decide what to
do. So, because we can train for
prediction and we properly penalize
these models, right? The problem with
LLMs in some sense is that they don't
understand numbers. They just say, "Did
I generate the next token correctly or
not?" So, if the next token is 200 or
2,000, it's the same amount of penalty.
But in relation of foundation models, if
my prediction is 1,000 off, the model
gets much more than if the prediction is
two or 1.5 off.
>> How do you do that penalization? What is
the mechanism for actually penalizing a
bad prediction?
>> Yeah, because we have loss function that
is actually not about was the next token
generated correctly, but we can kind of
measure the distance if you want to
think of it this way between the truth
and the prediction. And we penalize by
the amount of distance, not by was it
correct or not.
Right? And in text, you cannot do that
because there's no similarity between
tokens. Tokens are tokens and it's
either the correct one or it's the wrong
one. There is nothing in between.
>> In code, which is one of the
applications of LLMs, LLMs, right?
You do have some kind of penalization in
the whole RL loop where you might
penalize it as it compiles, as it do
something, does it do some of these
things. You're right, it's not accurate,
it's not perfect, but there is some kind
of guidance there, right?
>> In these domains where it's verifiable,
of course, RL has shown a really good
progress, but even there, the
verification signal is binary. It
compiles or it doesn't. It's not that
something is more accurate than
something else. It's just yes or no.
That's kind of what I'm trying to say.
But in these prediction use cases, you
get more information. You kind of know
how much you were wrong, and you can
tell that the model, and then the model
starts to learn these nuances in a
better way.
>> Nice. Is it also, again, for layman, is
it also kind of a backprop mechanism or
is it a different setting that feedback
back again?
>> It's the backprop. It's just the loss
functions are different.
>> Yeah, nice.
>> The penalty functions.
>> Right. From a calibration perspective,
typically, what is the proportion of
your training budget or your training
resource budget that goes into
calibration versus your general train?
>> Good question. I would say a large,
large majority of resources goes into
training. So, kind of calibration comes
in some sense for free. It's built into
the training process itself through the
usage of proper loss functions. And
also, I think what the point is, these
post-training phases in LLMs, those are
the ones that kind of lobotomize the
model. Here, we don't have to post-train
and say, "Oh, does the human prefer this
or not?" and things like that. So, that
kind of starts skewing the confidence of
LLMs, but here, we don't have to do
that. The quality of the output can be
objectively measured, and because of
that, the model gets much more kind of
reliable, consistent signal during
train.
>> What about in-context training during a
session? Does calibration, because you
don't have to a post-training kind of
phase, right? Could it mean that when
you're live in context, the predictions
can somehow be fed back in that session
or won't be equal in there?
>> Yeah, so the way in-context learning
would work in this case is that you
would give the model a set of kind of
historical examples, and then you would
ask it about something that you don't
know. And now, the model gets those
historical in context examples that are
of course use case, let's say customer
database specific, and then you give it
something that you don't know about. You
ask it to make a prediction, and this
pre-trained model is basically reasoning
over those historical examples that you
gave it to make you that prediction. And
what is interesting here because if I
give you the historical examples, the
model can take a couple of those away
and pretend as if it doesn't know it
doesn't know the outcome in the past,
make a prediction there, and it sees how
accurate it is.
And that gives you objective
non-hallucinated way to say this is how
accurate I am for this prediction,
right? It cannot be overconfident
because it can measure itself, let's
say, on the historic data.
>> Now, you also mentioned that this
explanation, I guess, comes with a score
of confidence, right?
And typically, is it a set of scores, a
set of likelihoods? Like is it per
prediction? I I guess how does a user of
this prediction absorb that and, you
know, practically use it?
>> Yeah, that's a great point. So, you
would get two things, right? Or three
things. You get a prediction, you get a
confidence interval accuracy estimate,
and then you also get the explanation
in natural language about why did the
model make that prediction. And the way
we do this, it's actually super cool.
It's allows us to basically back trace
the model and see what data is it
attending over.
All right? And then we can basically
look at that attention mechanism, the
tables, the columns, the rows that the
model is attending over, and then
synthesize that into an explanation. And
we can say prediction for this is like
that because of the data in this table,
the data in that table, and so on.
That's what I would say is the exciting
part is that you can truly make these
explanations not just by the signals or
features that somebody sought to
engineer, but actually directly from the
raw data. So, the fidelity or richness
of these explanations is actually quite
impressive. You kind of learn something
new because it's hidden in the data and
you didn't actually know about it. You
didn't have to pre-engineer it.
>> Interesting. So, it's almost like a
debugging trace.
>> Great point. It's also we see many times
it's a debugging trace, because what you
can easily detect with this is to say,
"Oh, actually I have some information
leakage. I have some data in there that
I shouldn't have in there." And things
like that. Exactly. So, you can think of
it as a debugging trace.
>> But instead of trace hitting endpoints
or methods or function calls, you're
actually talking about which piece of
data in your database you're asking.
What was the weight? What was the
process?
>> Exactly. It's about almost like
debugging the data in a sense, right?
Especially when things go wrong, it's a
super elegant way to debug what's
happening. Or when a prediction is made,
you can use it for justification and
things like that.
>> So, as you debug it, how would you use
this to effectively debug it? Let's say
I found a trace. I've noticed that
again, this is just visually for my own
modeling, right? You find that in this
query, the prediction used
table X and not Y. Or it used
relationship A and not B. Yeah. I'm I'm
assuming it looks like that, but maybe
not. But if you had that, what would you
do with it? And who would do it?
>> That's great, right? So, there are
several different ways. If you are the
one who's developing the model, what you
can learn from this is that maybe you
have a table in there that is leaking
information. Or maybe you learn that
some data is important for prediction,
but actually that data is not available
at the time of prediction. But the model
is going to use it. So, you can kind of
take that data away. Another way that
can happen is that if you see that model
is attending over particular table of
over a particular type of data, that
also tells you, "Oh, there is signal in
here." You can bring additional data,
link in another tables, and this way
improve the accuracy of the model. So,
it's both good for improving the model,
as well as kind of finding, I would say,
bugs in the data, having columns that
maybe, you know, somehow were in there,
but shouldn't be there because they are
backfilled and things like that. So, of
these use cases would be solved by this
by providing ideas on what you can do to
improve as well as kind of debugging the
data where the model is shockingly good
and you're like, "Hey, something seems
fishy here."
>> Yeah, it's almost like a really good
forensic investigator tool as well. You
know, you you don't know what you don't
know and you're finding out things that
you didn't know.
>> Exactly. You can think of it as a
forensic tool and you can also where it
becomes very useful is because you can
start asking these models what is called
technically counterfactual questions.
You can say, "If I do this, what would
happen? If I send this offer to the
customer, what happens to the customer?"
Right? So, now you can kind of test all
these alternative hypothesis and ask the
model, "Okay, like we had a use case for
sales lead scoring and then the person
who was using the system was like, "Hey,
why did you predict so low probability
of me closing this deal?" And you can go
back to the model and the model is like,
"Look, I'm looking at the data. Your
deal size is very large compared to
other deals. I'm looking here, you don't
have an executive sponsor. And also, by
the way, this data hasn't been updated
for 3 months."
Now, the salesperson can be like, "Ooh,
okay, actually, there is new
information. We forgot to update. Let's
put that data in." And you can query the
model again. Or you can start asking,
"Okay, I don't have an executive
sponsor. Let me figure that out." And
then, you can be also asking this
counterfactual question, which is like,
"Okay, so now if I offer the client 10%
discount, what happens to the
probability of closing?" This is kind of
an example Yeah, how this capability
could be used.
>> That's a really good example, actually.
So, how much of this, I'll use the word
fine-tuning loosely, how much of this
adding more data, doing more fine-tuning
or an RFM can you do before you might
say you hit the limit and you have to
retrain or go with a newer model? Is
there kind of any rough rule of thumb
there or is it just one day we'll get
there?
>> I would say generally more data that is
actually useful and relevant allows you
to train more accurate models. So, we
want to use the data that is relevant
and as much of it as possible. But also
these methods, you know, are not that
data hungry. We have use cases where
maybe we have an order of thousands of
examples. And we have use cases where we
have an order of tens of billions of use
cases. And the beautiful thing is that
you can basically then choose your model
size, architecture, that kind of fits
your needs.
>> Okay, so that sounds good. One big hot
topic is agentic systems, right? How do
you see this kind of interdependence,
symbiosis between RFMs and agentic
systems?
>> Yeah, we see a lot of traction there
because, you know, for agents, specially
in enterprise business settings, they
need to be able to make decisions. All
right, and even if you say, "I am a
customer support agent." That customer
support agent actually has a lot of
predictive decision-making tasks to make
before it reacts. Right, it's about
what's the lifetime value of this
customer? How likely is this customer
going to churn? What is the next best
action that I take to keep this
customer? What is the offer or
resolution I should offer to increase
the probability of customer not churning
and so on. Right? And today, I think we
are early in agents, so we get excited
about this almost like this kind of,
"Oh, let's retrieve some knowledge from
some knowledge base and reformat it and
things like that." But as these agents
become more business critical, more
autonomous, they need this
decision-making power and reasoning
ability over the enterprise structured
operational data to make the correct
decisions. Right? And if you now start
thinking about a customer agent, one of
course important thing is to talk, to
understand, and things like that. But at
the same time, it's like having the
right tone, giving the right offer, and
making sure that, you know, customers
are satisfied, that directly affects the
effectiveness. So, we see a lot of need
for that.
>> Could you share examples of where a
customer has switched their agent to use
an RFM versus a classical LLM, and how
it improved the outcome?
>> A great example is also in sales, right?
If you say about, let's understand the
probability of closing, uh let's
understand what's the next best action
to take here, let's understand what's
the next product to upsell to that
client so that they increase their
spend, let's understand what me as a
salesperson should do next to be more
effective. We see great results in these
types of domains. Uh LLMs cannot make, I
mean, they make this kind of good
human-level common-sense decisions, but
these dedicated predictive models who
have looked through all the patterns of
the past are just so much more accurate,
right? They're like 20-30% more accurate
than this kind of common-sensey LLM or
human can do. And we've done, like, for
example, with some sales teams, we ran
AB tests where one part of the sales
team would act based on these
predictions, and the other one would use
LLMs and existing tools, and it was a
huge difference. It was like 30%
difference in effectiveness of those
teams. Because they had this structured
data understanding, good quantitative
predictions, counterfactuals, and things
like that.
>> As you wrap up, I want to get some
practical guidance for software
engineers or data scientists who are
kind of in this space and want to
explore this. What would be the easiest
way to start exploring it? I mean, what
is the hello world of this?
>> Yeah, that's a great point. I would say
there is a couple of hello worlds, and
it depends maybe on the flavor or role,
technical sophistication, or I don't
know, of people. I think for
researchers, PyG, PyTorch Geometric, is
a great starting point. A real bench and
all this stuff. For people who just want
to use this, I think these tabular
foundation models, relational foundation
models are great and that is both open
source as well as basically public as
the case when people can start playing
with this. The one I'd recommend is
called Kumo RFM. So, if you go to k u m
o r f m like relational foundation
model.ai, want to start playing with
this. And this technology is also going
to be available soon in large data
warehouses like Snowflake and so on so
that it's kind of ready to use,
pre-installed. One doesn't have to worry
too much.
>> Sounds good. How can we learn more about
this and how can we follow you? Are
there conferences? Will you be speaking
at any of them?
>> Yeah, that's great. I try to publish our
research mostly on LinkedIn as well as
on X. So, on X I'm at Yura on LinkedIn
as well. And yeah, I attend a lot of
conferences, of course, the top AI
conferences like NeurIPS, ICLR and so
on. And then also try to go to meetups,
especially here in San Francisco where
there is strong developer AI community
hungry to to kind of learn the next
thing.
>> Thank you. Thank you. Any closing words
of advice before we wrap up?
>> It was a great conversation. I think for
me to summarize what's the key The key
here is essentially this structured
relational enterprise data is missing
modality in today's AI.
And what I'm saying is the world of
machine learning and predictive modeling
is getting heavily disrupted with the
technologies and approaches that I'm
talking about. So, relational deep
learning, relational foundation models.
And that's the next frontier and that's
where the future is going. So, I do
encourage people to get familiar with
these things, be it machine learning
engineers, data scientists, as well as
business units and so on.
>> Thank you. Hands off engineers.
>> Software engineers.
>> Thank you so much.
>> Thank you. Thank you. This has been a
very enlightening and very insightful
chat. I've learned so much and as have
our listeners. Thank you. This is Sriram
Padmanabhan with Jure on relation
foundational models. Thank you.
>> [music]
>> Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more [music]
about the podcast, including other
episodes, visit our website at
se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
[music] through our Slack channel at
seradio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
>> [music]
>> This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.